[Music]
well hello everybody good evening good
day to all of you welcome to ask abhijit
uh it's great to see you all let's see
who all is there i can see annamai
abbasis
sudhir chaudhary viki chahal rudra
rajiv tamagna biswas vms gaming akhil
the boseman shashank
and so many other people good evening
good day to all of you i hope you're
doing well i can see lots more people
saying hi hi everybody hi
it's great to see you all it's great to
see you all
so as you know today is a live video
chat session and for that i'm gonna have
to paste
i'm gonna have to post
uh the link
the link for joining so let's do it
let's do it now
here is the link i should i think you
should be able to see it now let me pin
it up
yes it is pinned
so the link is pinned you guys can start
joining and there are certain rules that
i have put in place
these are the rules
one question per person
please keep your questions short and
precise and if you appeared on video
chat yesterday please do not join i want
new people to join today
if you joined yesterday please don't try
to join us join today
i mean if you appeared if you spoke to
me yesterday please don't join i would
like new people to join
and if i see people joining who have
joined yesterday i will
i will
have to remove them
so please understand that
and let me put this over here there you
go
so so so let's begin let's begin uh
let's bring in somebody let's bring in
mr ghihan jhin
hello sayama
hello
hi yes you are audible where are you
from
sir i'm from rajasthan
all right all right what's your question
sir
so my question is sir as it is said that
lord buddha was the ninth author of lord
vishnu
then why there is no proper mention of
lord vishnu and his eighth after in
japan tales if jatak tells our stories
of his previous birds and how jatak
tales can even form
if he was ninth avatar of your vision
i i am not an expert in the jatak tales
and the afters of lord vishnu i am
afraid i will not be able to answer your
question i mean i don't have any
expertise expertise on this matter
sorry you have another other question
i'll give you one more chance
yes sir
that in your previous video video yes
you have said that tipu sultan was very
barbaric and was not a great ruler so
just i wanted to know the reasons
because he committed so many atrocities
he destroyed so many temples he killed
so many people he committed massacres
there is a community in i don't i don't
remember which what is the name but they
don't celebrate diwali even today
because their ancestors were massacred
on diwali day and there were so many
churches and christians that were
destroyed i mean churches were destroyed
christians were massacred christians
were forcibly converted
i mean if you look at the record of this
person's career and you see the the
account of the atrocities that are in
writing you will understand that there
is no other way to
no other description for such a person
except for calling him a barbarian a
brutal monster
so that that's it what it is you can
look it up all the records are available
in the public domain right so that's why
he still reported as a hero in our
textbooks because our historians have a
certain agenda to make young people like
you think that our oppressors were the
heroes and our heroes were actually uh
primitive barbaric useless weak losers
you know they want to inculcate a
defeatist mentality in indian so that
they can keep following the west and
stay colonized so that's what
is the reason
all right okay okay thank you
thank you nice meeting you sir nice
meeting you bye
okay uh let us bring in somebody else
let's bring in mr um
udit
hello from yes sir hello
uh did you read the rules sir oh sorry
okay let's bring somebody else
uh let's bring in mr ashu
hello
i can't hear you sir
hello sir
hi i can hear you now yes sir where are
you from
yours i'm being fair and obvious thank
you so much
sir i'm from bihar sir
uh very nice very nice what's your
question
right now i am staying inside gurgaon
okay okay great so so my question is sir
according to you who is the most
influential scientist of all time
and is it newton or is it einstein and
why sir um
and
sir
as you are also a physicist so according
to you who has done the tremendous job
in the field of physics according to you
and who is the biggest inspiration in
your life as a physicist so um you can
tell that
right right okay good question so you
know uh it's
impossible to
to pinpoint just one person as the
greatest of all time if you i i would
say that every century there is one or
two people there are one or two people
who are the greatest so if you look at
the 20th century 2-0 20th century i
would say it's most likely people like
isaac newton
uh
and the people who develop quantum
mechanics
you know schuldinger heisenberg niels
bohr and so so and so what they all
collectively have a huge contribution
among those head and shoulders above
them is
albert einstein obviously and in the
previous century in the 19th century
most likely it's james clerk maxwell the
person who
the physicist who gave us the laws of
electromagnetism the maxwell equations
and so on so i would not i i don't see
any one person as the greatest of all
time i think in any given period of time
there are one or two individuals who are
really really
among the greatest of all time and uh
most likely i would say that newton i
don't consider him to be that great
because see
uh he is cons he is given the credit of
developing calculus but we know that
that was all brought in from india it
was the knowledge of calculus was
present in india at least 100 years
before newton was born
and all of that was transmitted to the
west by the arabs so i do not consider
him to be that great of course he built
upon the knowledge that was acquired
from the indians and so on so he's one
of the greats and he himself said
cryptically that if i have achieved some
great things it's because i am standing
on the shoulder of giants
that's what he said i'm we don't know
which giants he was referring to most
likely ancient indians so that's what i
would say and as far as i'm concerned my
greatest inspiration well i am not
inspired by any one person i'm inspired
by all the great physicists all the
great scientists who have come before
not only physicists even other other
sciences and all that and other scholars
other great people so i don't have any
one person i worship i don't believe in
hero worship and all and neither should
anybody
look at everybody and if you if you
really seek heroes or idols you should
have a bunch of people from whom you can
uh be inspired for certain qualities so
let's say you have certain uh
scientists in which certain qualities
appeal to you then certain leaders or
kings in which certain qualities appeal
to you certain
business people whose certain qualities
appeal to you that's the sort of thing
you should have if you're not hero
worship one or two people that is a
little bit counterproductive in my
opinion
all right sir i hope i answered your
question
yes sir thank you sir
uh thank you i love you very much
talking to yourself
very nice meeting you thank you thank
you thank you so much
bye good night
okay
um
let's bring in
monica but good evening ma'am
yes i can hear you yes ma'am i can hear
you
this is so nice to be here sir i am a
great fan of yours and both of my
children are working with great queen of
yours sir it's a pleasure to be here so
my question is like where are you from
uh i belong to uttarakhand
okay
yeah but i'm based in delhi i belong to
yes uh yeah
sir my question is like uh
in past few years that i have what i've
seen is uh the worship of sign baba has
increased
do you know it has crossed the limits
and everywhere it it means so many
people are following sai bhava
so i just wanted to know the history
because uh as far as our vedas and all
uh scriptures are concerned i did not
get any reference from them so just can
you please guide me thank you so much
okay so yeah sure uh very good question
uh
i believe there is uh there are two
three uh
people who have been given this term
cyber this this title of sai baba right
there was uh this uh one gentleman from
shirdi in i think maharashtra right who
is called travis baba and there was
another gentleman from the south of
india the guy with the big hair
who was also called sai baba so so
and obviously these are these are recent
these are people who lived recently very
recently 19th and 20th century so
obviously there will be no mention of
these people in the vedas firstly so the
thing is this in in
any polytheistic uh culture and our
hinduism what we call hinduism now is a
platheistic belief system which says
that there is divinity there is the
presence of god in every individual even
in animals even in plants and all that
and some people if they develop their
themselves they have more of it some
people have less
so it is believed that some people
become avatars of vishnu because of the
great things they did right they are
called avatars of vishnu for instance
and similarly some people because of
special qualities they are regarded as
kind of gods by by certain sections of
society
and i believe that's what happened with
uh shirdi sai baba and the other sai
baba i am not uh
an expert in their life and career and
all that so i don't know how how true or
not true it would be that they were so
great i have not studied their life and
i'm not very much aware of their history
so i think it is up to individual people
what they want to believe if they feel
that some person has some extra divinity
in them they can worship them i would
say we should worship
the gods
of our vedas of ours of our scriptures
and all that that's my personal opinion
but if somebody wants to differ from
that opinion they have the right to do
that i am not going to tell them what to
do but that's my personal opinion so i
don't know about these two gentlemen who
are called cyber i don't know how great
they were what their achievements were
that is simply something i don't have
the knowledge of so that's all i can say
about this
thank you so much
finally it's like uh individual belief
system means
if anybody finds okay okay fine thank
you so much thank you so much nice
meeting nice meeting you thank you nice
to meet you thank you samuel thank you
so much
thank you bye
okay let's just bring in
somebody
uh let's bring in mr
shamant
hello
namaste hi
namaste namaste where are you from sir
sir i am from bengaluru
all right
okay so first of all i'd like to thank
you
yeah i'd like to thank you we are very
lucky to have you
thank you so much thank you my question
is uh
we all know about ancient india india
was prosperous so but in last thousand
years we know what has happened
so at present we can see people are
mentally colonized
all such things so
culture and my question is about culture
so culture is something like people say
it's not required something like that so
can you please tell me the importance of
indian culture and
how we can decolonize the indian minds
so like
people rejecting indian culture are
considered more indian like it's
somewhat unnecessary people say like
that so this is my question sir
yes yes it's a very very good question
very valid point that today in today's
society if you reject indian culture if
you denigrate indian culture if you make
fun of it then you are supposed to be
you are considered to be more advanced
and more more modern and all that
nonsense the thing is this what is the
importance of culture in any society
culture
gives you a set of principles and moral
values that you need to follow that you
can follow or you should follow in order
to live a fruitful productive and useful
life not just for yourself but for the
whole of society so every society every
civilization has a certain set of moral
values that it believes in these are the
core fundamental moral values and
principles for instance in india we say
that uh ahinsa parma dharma satyam and
all that
all of that right so we have this
emphasis on speaking the truth we have
an emphasis on being good not being ha
not hurting other people and we believe
in non-violence but we also believe that
we have to establish non-violence if
there is violence against us we have to
destroy it and defeat it and and so on
so forth so every society every culture
has a set of moral values and principles
if you give up if you abandon culture
then you are suddenly rootless in your
adrift then you will have to come up
with a set of principles of your own and
for most people it is very difficult to
do that you know everybody needs some
kind of anchoring
in which they can uh
that serves as a moral and ethical
reference point for their life everybody
needs that and if you uh give up your
culture give up whatever values your
society has then you become morally
adrift and that's why people go into
doing crimes and
indulging in behaviors that are harmful
for themselves like smoking drugs
alcoholism and whatnot right so if you
give up culture that's what happens it
it doesn't only apply to india it
applies to the west the west for the
past 1000 years plus
was uh
practicing various forms of christianity
now there is a certain moral structure
in that there is a certain uh
set of principles that is definitely
part of christianity now what you're
seeing in the u.s and in the in europe
etc they're abandoning christianity
because they are now beginning to see
what it is all truly about whatever the
reason but they are abandoning
abandoning it and now because of that
the society is morally adrift they don't
have a set of values and principles to
uh to anchor themselves too and that's
why you seeing all these child i mean
one parent families you see this very
high rate of divorce you see uh
so many uh
so many problems there is drug abuse
there is crime and all that
so that's what happens when you abandon
not religion but culture religion and
culture are separate things i mean they
could be together but they are also
separate you can have culture without
religion too i mean you can be an
atheist but you can still follow
the principles of your culture so today
what's happening in india is that there
is a concerted effort
to demean and
eradicate hinduism from india and not
just hinduism all dharmic the entire
dharmic structure is there is a very
strong
effort that is being made right now to
to to destroy it to to eradicate it from
india and the media is part of it i'm
not saying all of the media but a
significant portion of the media
a significant portion of the
entertainment industries is engaged in
this effort and almost all of the
academia is also engaged in this effort
all our textbooks everything all our the
constitution the laws everything
so what happens is that because of this
youngsters are being raised rootless
they are not grounded in their own
culture and as a result they feel that
indian culture is backward misogynistic
blah blah blah blah blah
and because of that they are trying to
uh
ape
ape the west
and we know what's happening in the west
it is already rootless
there is so much promiscuity there is
all the crime there is drug abuse and
what not what not is there right all of
that so that's now what indians are
trying to emulate because of mental
colonization they think the west is
superior the west is better they think
if somebody has white skin they are
superior to us and we should just
blindly follow what they're doing and
that is dragging india down
so that's the reason why these people
are doing it in order to keep india
colonized because there are there is
money flowing into india for precisely
this particular effort so that's why
it's happening
and what needs to be done is we need to
somehow find ways to
uh
revive our culture uh educate especially
the children
in what is right what is wrong and what
their culture is and so on that this
needs to be a long-term concerted effort
and hopefully the government which we
are electing and who to whom we are
paying taxes will
someday wake up and do something about
this but uh if the government is not
doing it the people need to wake up and
they should also stick together work
together and try to revive indian
culture
that's what i can say
yeah thank you sir thank you
good question sir nice meeting you thank
you thank you sir nice meeting you
thank you bye
all right
up i have
banuji
did you read the rules sir why are you
here i i
have clearly mentioned that
sir i'm not joined yesterday
oh you did not join the city yes you
found the loophole in the rules perfect
what's your question
hi you are very smart
sir why in bollywood jhangir was shown
as a chocolate boy and a very romantic
character even though he was very high
and ruthless
he also killed
arjun devji who was six guru
yeah okay good question like i mentioned
just now bollywood the entire
entertainment industry is engaged in a
concerted effort to distort the mean
indian culture and history they always
portray indian history in a certain
specific way distorted way they portray
the oppressors as our saviors and they
portray our culture as inferior our
heroes as losers
right they have they are engaged in this
concerted effort for several decades
decades in doing this
and they they no longer represent indian
culture correctly
they they are no longer representatives
of indian culture and they they are
engaged in distorting everything so
that's the reason they do it right and
there is foreign
i'm assuming i don't know for sure but
i'm assuming there must be some foreign
funding flowing into these people at
least some of them some of them i think
that's also come in the media and all
that so it's not something controversial
that i'm saying
so some of them may have some foreign
influences because of which they're
doing this so the entire effort not only
of bollywood or some parts of bollywood
but of certain parts of the media of the
entire academic system about government
policies everything is to be demean
indian culture distort indian history
and portray our oppressors as our great
saviors and our heroes as the great
losers it's very simple so that's why
it's happening sir
okay
thank you sir i will not join for next
two weeks
okay thank you so much it's always nice
to see you anyway good questions as
always thank you thank you bye
yes yes he was right he did not break
the rules
okay let's bring in um
let's bring in mr suraj
hello
hi sir i can't believe that you know i
came in confidence with you but it's
like really what's up here you are
i posted on facebook about you a lot
so it means oh thank you so much thank
you thank you so much
i'm from mumbai itself and my native
island
very nice very nice nice to meet you sir
what's your question
so my question is related to uh kind of
science and mystery uh so basically i
wanted to know that in science we
we are quite well aware that
energy can either be created nor it can
be destroyed it can only be transferred
from one
you know one form to another
so
my question is that
life is energy and
once you die the energy is released so
it is not a destruction of energy but
why can't we prove that there is life
after death or that energy is being
transferred to some other form
okay
uh see the thing is this we don't have a
scientific definition of life and
we don't have a
clear specific unambiguous definition of
what is life
so life seems to be a biological
phenomenon right we know what is life
when we see it we know whether something
is alive or it is not alive whether
something is a living thing or a
non-living thing we know it and we also
know when an animal dies or a person
dies i mean we can see that this person
is no longer alive so we can see it we
can sense it but we don't have a
scientific definition clear scientific
definition because somebody who has died
whose heart has stopped it can possibly
be revived within a certain time and
even a person whose heart has stopped
for like 10 minutes their brain activity
may be going on so what is the
definition what is the dividing line
between life and death that's the first
thing secondly
uh
so is life about your brain's
consciousness is it about the beating of
your heart what exactly it is we don't
have a definition there is no uh
consensus of that
and
so so we have this physical body
and in this body there is there are
there are various chemicals and various
substances etc and there is a certain
process that goes on continuously a
bunch of chemical reactions and what not
which which constitutes all of that
constitutes life
now is that
it is matter
it is matter right this is all matter
it's not it's not electricity it is not
energy
uh according to e equals squared in
quantum physics we know that matter and
energy are equivalent they are
interchangeable etc but what we have is
matter we have electrical impulses going
on inside electrochemical impulses and
all right right so once somebody dies
what happens
the body is the same but certain
processes have stopped
certain biochemical process processes
have stopped
which has
uh ended the the living form of the body
and it's no longer a living form
now which energy is lost do we know if
energy if any kind of energy is lost
do we have any evidence of that that's
the question right science is all about
measurable evidence observable evidence
and
observable phenomena we observe that the
breathing stops the heartbeat stops now
the beating of the heart stops maybe the
brain activity stops so at a certain
time we are 100 sure that this person is
no longer alive but did any energy
disappear somewhere we don't know right
we don't we cannot measure that right
right and there doesn't seem to be any
loss of energy instantaneously or any
such thing so the problem is that we are
not able to observe any such phenomenon
that this is some some x amount of
energy in whatever joules has been
removed from the body and it has gone
somewhere else we don't mean we don't
ever observe that i'm not saying it may
not be the case
but within the limitations of science
and our observational powers and
instruments we are not able to see that
and science is about these limitations
we have very hard limitations that we
have to follow otherwise we are no
longer doing science we are doing
something else so that's why we cannot
say for sure that such a thing happens
so we know that
we know that kinetic is getting
converted into potential energy but we
don't know how quickly we can revive it
bike to a kinetic energy after that
i don't know which kinetic or potential
energy is in you know in your body you
know there is electrochemical energy
and all kinds of other other forms of
energy it's not kinetic energy is newton
in physics you drop a ball it's kinetic
in the if it is high it is potential and
so on that is a simple neutron in
physics in the body you have
electrochemistry and a lot of
biochemistry and much more so it's not
as simple as it seems to be it's very
complex we don't know what is the
dividing line
okay sir
thanks a lot all right
thank you thank you good question sir
thank you bye bye
all right
uh who do we have
let's bring in mr um
mr robin
hello
hi
after living here for three or four
years we have seen like when indians
meet they usually don't uh like interact
so much like namaste hi like we have
seen in like these african people
basically they have in so much manner
like they are very very like interactive
but indians don't like even north indian
north city they don't like interact so
much so is there any is there is any
like cultural thing or why this indian
is like so much not not in interactive
or
you know like making it feel like we are
indians we are brothers unlike like
european or even these africans they are
very brother type brotherhood
very very interesting uh observation you
have made and i agree with you i think
uh
uh who was that guy there's this very
famous comedian russell peters he says
that
indians when they're abroad they hate
each other they don't want to meet each
other they they there is this attitude i
think it is because of a certain
inferiority complex that indians have
that when they go abroad
when most indians go and settle abroad
or live abroad for some time they try to
pretend that they are foreigners they
try to give up their indian identity
they put on this fake accent these fake
mannerisms and all and when they see
another indian they want to stay away
otherwise we'll have to speak in the
indian accent again and all that you
know i think that is the thing
because i have also been abroad i've
seen this in in with my own eyes indians
like to avoid other indians that they
don't know but otherwise indians also
have this other interesting phenomenon
that when indians live abroad they will
all if they know each other let's say
there are like seven indians working for
a single company for the same company
then they will all have their houses
next to each other and they will only
mingle with each other also that is also
there and you will see these uh
temporary workers who go to the us for
three months six months they will all
live five six guys in one house
and try to minimize the cost and all
that so there are these interesting
sociological phenomena that you see with
indians living abroad but what you spend
what you specifically mentioned that
indians try to avoid each other and all
that if they don't know each other
that may be because the indians try to
become
western and try to pretend like their
foreigners you know they try to put on
this fake accent and all that so that
may be the case i it's complex but your
what your what your observation is is
indeed correct
so that's what i can guess why why they
will be behaving this way possibly
okay
all right nice meeting you sir thank you
thank you bye
okay let's bring in
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
samudra
hello
uh
not very clear
hello
[Music]
i'm i'm sorry your voice is not clear at
all unfortunately
okay let's bring you in at some other
time let's bring in somebody else um
let's uh bring in
homeschooling abhishek
hello
hello sir hope you're fine
hello i am very well i'm very well how
are you doing
i'm good sir so i have this question
uh so i'm from delhi sir
okay okay go ahead please
so the so-called archaeological survey
of india the founded in 18th century
is maintaining the human use tomb very
well
but i recently saw the raja raja raja
chola
decaying in some part of india's advisor
yes yes excellent question very good
question very good observation what you
will see we have to go back to the
origin in the history of the asi to
understand its attitude and its behavior
the asi i think it was uh started in the
19th century somewhere
most likely 1860s
1860s that is the 19th century yesterday
there is an idea oh yes yes yeah so in
the 1860s like you say most likely yeah
so and it was founded by the british by
the british foreign colonizers and
occupiers of india and the real reason
for the founding of this uh
of this institution was to go and search
for various indian antiquities
loot them and transfer them to the uk if
you look at the uk if you look at the
various museums in the uk london museum
etc these are crime scenes everything is
stolen from india enormous amounts of
treasure and
various carvings statues priceless
treasures are stolen from india they are
they're all uh
collected over there and displayed over
there and there is much more that is not
displayed it is all stored and so much
more is in the hands of private
collectors the the individual i don't
remember his name the person who founded
the ace i was the first
head of the asi he was himself a big
thief of indian antiquities
much of what was discovered by the asi
and restored by the asia was transferred
to the uk and it became his private
property
so the asi its original mission
was to seek out is was to find seek out
and collect priceless indian antiquities
and transfer most of them to the uk now
today
they cannot do that to the uk but what
you will find is that there are so many
of these asi
asi protected monuments they will not
allow you to go there and and take a
video
i wonder why
they will not allow indian citizens to
go go to those monuments and take videos
unless you pay them a lot of money
but they will not take care of the of
the monument and you will find that so
many temples etc that are under the as
so supposed protection their murtis
their idols and everything which is of
you of value is all stolen
you will find so many harappan era sites
saraswati civilization era sites that
are officially under asi protection and
there are there are completely pillaged
and i can show you online so much so
many artifacts from that that era of our
history are being sold online there is a
site called vatican.com go there and see
so many indus valley
sites are visit
uh artifacts are for sale online over
there so the asi is not doing anything
because it was founded as an institution
as an organization that whose only
intention was to steal
valuable artifacts from india that was
the beginning of the asi and i believe
that over the years after 1947 there
have been some asi uh
some people in the asia who have done
really good work so there have been a
few archaeologists who have done really
really good work i'm sure there are a
few even today who are doing good work
but overall the asi is run by
bureaucrats who have no interest in
archaeology they are just bureaucrats
and
the the attitudes the colonial attitudes
still persist and the contempt for
indian culture and indian heritage still
continues so they will
uh focus on maintaining turkic monuments
mughal monuments invader monuments yes
sir yes they will let every or every
actual indigenous indian cultural
heritage just fall into disrepair and
even be auctioned off online so that's
what i'm what's happening i'm sure there
are some good individuals in the asi i
will not say that all of them are bad
and all of them are like this
but overall
the attitude of the asi is that of
complete neglect
that's the best thing i can say about
them that they are neglecting our
heritage i can say much worse about them
but i will say the best thing i can say
is that they are neglecting already so
what needs to happen what needs to
happen is that the asi needs to be
disbanded by the government yes stop
funding disband them and start a new
institution that is comprised in which
you only have professional
archaeologists who are really well-known
and we need to have one world-class
museum at least in every state in india
that's what needs to be yes so that's
what i can say sir very good question
thank you sir you are inspiration sir
thank you so much thank you so much nice
thank you bye
all right um whom shall we bring in
let's bring in
somebody
hello
good evening good evening
good evening ma'am where are you from
i'm from kolkata
let's hear your question
so can you hear me now
yes sir uh so my question is that as we
all know that uh
governor general lord william bentik was
a person who abolished the sati prata so
what was so my question is that what was
the reason that he actually did that
like uh should we consider that as a
favor towards us or and what was the
role of raja ramon roy and you know
doing like behind this
okay good question i'm gonna put you in
mute
so um
firstly i'm gonna answer your question
for sure it's a very good question
firstly what i would suggest is there is
a conversation on this channel
with uh dr mean oxygen she has gone into
this in in very good detail so i would
recommend that you and anybody else who
wants to learn about this should see
that conversation it's about one hour
long now to answer your question there
was no such thing as sati pratha pratha
means a tradition
a tradition like sati did not really
exist there
and you know what the british and the
europeans have said they said they they
have portrayed this thing
in this manner that there was a
compulsion
in india for widows to be burned alive
with their dead husbands they were
forced to be burned this is how they
were portrayed and if you look at the
records
that they were maintaining
the first place the british colonized
was bengal which is why bengal is the
most mentally colonized today
not all but to a large extent i would
just say that you know i'm not
generalizing but you you see that more
there so the first place they colonized
was bengal and initially you will find
that they were taking record keeping
records of what was happening in bengal
and there was almost no mention almost
no mention whatsoever of the the
so-called practice of bright burning
then the missionaries got involved and
then suddenly from zero the number of
cases per year started going beyond ten
thousand twenty thousand all of a sudden
by magic
okay and then indian writers like ram
mohan roy and various other bengali
writers started writing about this great
evil in hindu society which needs to be
reformed
and for generations they kept writing
about it and today bengali believe that
this was a very deeply entrenched
tradition in bengal but it's not the
case it's all lies missionary lies made
up fabricated lies okay
and the funny thing is this that when
this individual william bentik the
so-called lord william bentik he came to
india and before he came to india he had
already announced his intention to
abolish this practice so he comes to
india or
issues the proclamation puts his
signature on that and you know what
strange
he his
abolition of sati was so magically
powerful
that from the next day onwards
there was not a single case of satin
bengal
it
disappeared overnight yesterday until
yesterday you had 10 000 20 000 cases
per year
and from today onwards there are zero
cases magic
the greatest reformer of all time
william bentik these are all lies but
the problem is that we are taught all of
this is fact in our textbooks and all of
our people they believe that bengal and
in india you had this horrific tradition
of forcibly burning women alive when
their husbands died it is a lie
it was
this practice you will find a few
instances over the centuries so if you
look at the conversation with dr minak
jain you will she will mention that
there have been a few practice few
instances in all of the cases when a
woman decided to do to do this
she would be dissuaded by her friends by
her family by brothers sisters everybody
they would plead with her please don't
do this there are so many records of
this and eventually if she decided it
was her her choice nobody would stop her
but it was always the woman's choice and
there have been only a few instances
instances of this happening typically it
happened more in rajasthan among the
rajputs among the royal families of the
rajputs
and the johar tradition was totally
different from that it was like they had
no option that it was better to burn
yourself alive and destroy your body
than to even let your dead body body
fall in the hands of the turks
right so that's how it was the role of
ram mohan roy i mean i do not want to go
much deeper into it because it will
start another hue and cry but uh what i
can say is that this is all a lie
william bentik was not a magician the
the practice was not there at all right
that's what i can say
all right sir all right so it's always a
pleasure thank you sir
nice meeting you thank you so much thank
you
bye
okay uh
whom shall i bring uh let's bring in mr
rahul
hello
uh hi sir i'm audible
yes yes you're audible sir yeah sorry
i'm from
i'm i'm from mp
okay okay my question was actually i am
a cindy so my question was that
uh like sindh as a like as a
geographical location it was like very
hard hit when the turkic invaders or
islamic invaders came in
so
and and it is believed to be like at
that time when the
islamic invasions were happening and
so like or they converted and brutally
like murdered and converted
at least 80 percent of people were
converted to islam and maybe 20 percent
were left
so like
like it is some somewhere it is
considered to be like he's a
uh
avatar of
vishnuji so uh and the sindhi language
so uh do you think that
the sindhi language was prevalent at the
time of harappan or indus or saraswati
civilization or it came in much later
and your thoughts on the sindhi people
uh my thoughts
on the sunday people is that they're one
of the peoples of of india the sindhi
people are indians i mean today many
sundays are in pakistan it's a temporary
phenomenon we will reintegrate them when
the time is right these are as indian as
anybody else bengali gujaratis
manipuri's bengali anybody else right
uh so about
the geographical location of sindh it is
to the western part of india
for sure that's why it was easier i mean
it was one of the first parts of india
to bear the brunt of the turkic and
first the arabic invasions and the
turkey conventions which came
subsequently so i think it is believed
that there was this this
person individual called mohammed bin
qasim who was the first among the arabs
to to try and to attempt invading india
and there was some amount of success i
believe in sindh raja dahir got involved
in one of these invasions and
i believe he died and there were some
terrible atrocities so yes because of
the location geographical location is to
the west western part of india uh the
westernmost part of india historically
has been balochistan the border of india
and persia and then you had sindh so
sindh always bore the brunt sindh
afghanistan
and these western regions bore the brunt
of the turkic and other invasions the
most and they were the first regions to
fall to the invaders yes
so uh so yeah that's what happened and
like you mentioned uh over time all the
people got converted to the foreign
religion and that's what we witnessed
today so the demographics have changed
the religious demographic graphics are
very different today than what they have
historically been
so that's what i can say now about the
sindhi language it is one of the newer
uh
descendants of prakrit languages so the
oldest if you go back two thousand years
two and a half thousand years the
classical age of india
at that time the main language
civilization language and the overall
language that was spoken everywhere was
was classical sanskrit or panini and
sanskrit so that was the main language
spoken everywhere and eventually what
happened is that in different parts of
india
the language evolved and it kind of got
mildly corrupted it's called upper
branch the process of upper branch which
means that the language evolves and
changes and the words kind of
undergo some kind of
change so that gave rise to a bunch of
new languages which were all daughter
languages of sanskrit these are called
the prakrits these are the prakrit
languages and from the prakrits there
came newer languages it's always a
continuing process
and from that you got like languages
like
old gujarati which gave rise to marwari
maywa gujarati that is spoken today and
there is a
very similar similarity in gujarati
and rajasthani and cindy also there is a
similarity there yes of course because
the reason for that is that these are
all geographically contiguous regions
these are all neighboring states the
people are more or less similar the
people their origins are more or less
similar and the languages will obviously
be very similar so if you look at
gujarati if you look at rajasthan or
marwadi mewari even if you look at
cynthia or even if you look at balochi
these are very similar languages
even balochi is very similar to sindhi
and gujarati and mayweather
etc so that's how it happens the
language evolves over time even if you
look at the old persian language that
was spoken during the so-called
western or or
accommodate times in persia that itself
was an upper branch language of sanskrit
it was a descendant language of
so this entire region from india to the
middle east was actually one
uh
geo-ethnic continuum the same people in
different places and their languages
evolved differently so sindhi just like
the other languages of india is one of
those newer evolved languages it must
have
it must have emerged sometime in the
past 1000 years from an older language
which is the mother language of of
sindhi and eventually if you go back in
time you will arrive at sanskrit so
that's how it went
thank you all right sir
nice meeting you sir thank you good
question thank you
all right
let's uh
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
sai rakshit
hello hello how are you
i am very well how are you doing sir
i am very good sir so my question to you
is related to history as well as coming
from
i am from
chennai
nice to meet you hello everybody
yes thank you so much sir so my question
to you is related to history and
political current political science sir
that post-independence when we framed
our constitution
we have adopted secularism
it's a very good choice i myself am
secular i respect everyone
okay sir like it's my personal opinion
of course of course i respect your
opinion
but my opinion is why was it chosen
why was secularism chosen to govern an
entire country like india
i mean we like okay now we have our
neighbors pakistan says proudly yes
bangladesh says yes
china says we are strong atheists
we see we don't have any identity
because we're secular i mean yes turkey
is also secular their people are secular
that's what i believe like i have i've
heard that their first at personal level
they're secular but they recognize
themselves as islamic country
so why did our leaders choose secularism
as a core concept to govern our country
is it
that uh
our national leaders had some hindu
hatred
or good questions
this is what i want to know from you sir
you sir have asked a very good question
all right so so congratulations on
asking a very good question now let me
answer that
uh
so
the people whom we regard as our
founding fathers founding fathers as our
leaders were not really our leaders
they did not represent india they were
not representative of the
vast diversity of india so the
individuals the group of individuals who
formed the so-called constituent
assembly of india right
if you look at them how did they make it
to the constituent assembly was there an
election
from all the different parts of india
and each each part of india elects one
person to represent them in the
constituent assembly no they did not
happen these people were drawn from an
earlier election i wrote i think it was
the 1943 or something like that 41 was
it one of these years look it up
yes yes you're right sir so from that
election a large part of the constituent
assembly was drawn now this election if
you look at the details which are
available you will find that it
represented only 13 percent of indians 1
3 13 of indians all right so this was
not a representative election of the
people of india and from that you pull
out a bunch of people who put them in
the constituent assembly and a lot of
the other people in the constituent
assembly were nominated by the princely
states who are all puppets of the
british so what you find is that this
so-called democratic process was not
democratic at all it was all people who
were
essentially beholden to the foreign
occupiers of india and all they did was
to transform the 1935 one of the 1935
acts of the british
into a new framework into a slightly
different framework and they call it the
new constitution of india it is entirely
european and western in origin there is
nothing indian in it so how can it be
the constitution of india secondly
after the frame this the framed this
so-called constitution they put we the
people blah blah blah on
on the front page yes
but if you look at the way democracy
works let's let's see how the americans
uh adopted their constitution so their
so-called founding fathers therefore
they made the constitution then the
constitution was put to a vote and every
adult white male in america was allowed
to vote yes or no women were not allowed
of course and blacks and native
americans were not humans so they were
not allowed but all adult white males
were given the choice of accepting or
rejecting the constitution now in india
after these individuals framed drafted
the constitution they did not put it to
a vote and asked the people of india by
are you willing to accept this or not is
it palatable to you or do you find it is
wrong this was never done the
constitution has till date not been
ratified by the people of india and
therefore it does not represent the
people of india and that's why there are
all these clauses that are so badly
anti-indian civilization that even
somebody who has any
anybody who has any sense if they
actually examine the events and the
constitution they will realize how wrong
it is but what happens is that we are
taught in our history textbooks and in
our schools
that this was a democratic process and
then the constitution is so large 500
plus pages that nobody has the time to
read it so we just say oh yeah we have a
constitution and we will worship it
so that is the way the people of india
have been duped and that's why it is so
very badly uh anti-indian civilization
and culture so your point is very very
uh correct that
you know it's a personal choice whether
you want to be secular or not secularism
is a western concept what we believe in
india for thousands of years is that
every human being has the
is equal everybody should get the same
rights we should respect diversity
plurality other people's cultures or
other people's traditions we believe
that and you can call that secularism if
you want so i that that is something i
also believe we should respect everybody
you live in your country you can
practice your religion your culture but
don't try to tell me what to do in my
country and similarly i will not tell
you what to do in your country it should
be like that mutual respect but that's
not how it works in indian secularism
and that's why the
the outline that i just gave you that's
why it happened that way that's why we
are where we are
thank you so much sir thank you
thank you good question nice meeting you
bye nice meetings
thank you bye
okay
uh
let's bring in mr bhushan
hello
hello sir
hello how are you from
where are you from
currently in chennai
okay very nice very nice
sir my question is that uh
does the central government have enough
power to
uh free all the temples from the nation
if they
have i believe the central government
has the power to pass a law that says
that the temple should be treated
the way all other religious monuments of
other other communities are treated
every other non-hindu religious
community is given the right to
administer the temples in any way in
whatever way they want according to
their uh
religious tradition for whatever it is
but hindus are denied this right i
believe the central government has the
power to
i'm gonna mute yourself there's a lot of
noises i'm gonna meet you
okay
so i believe the central government has
the power
to pass a law
that says that hindu temples will be
freed and
sir i'm going to keep you muted because
there's a lot of noise coming in so
yes sir okay it's fine
i've got my answer thank you sir
you got it
let me finish it anyway so what i'm
saying is that central government has
the power to do it
it is up to them whether they choose to
do it or not
that's what i would say
so uh why are they not doing it i think
we should ask them because i don't have
the answer
all right
sir all right thank you nice meeting you
okay let's bring in um mr chaitanya
hello hello sir
hello sir how are you hi where are you
from
i am
a lot of people don't know but this town
is known as the southern kashi of india
and the food is excellent isn't it yes
yes
excellent
okay what's your question sir
uh so my question is uh i just i will
just read it out
in ancient times there were many
civilizations and they had their
respective religions and methods of
practice
like the greeks romans and ancient
egyptian civilization and after the
abrahamic revolution in middle east
only one civilization that is this vedic
civilization of india has continued to
exist
and we see there are people still
performing yagya zahuti's and people
practicing dhyana yoga so what are the
reasons or specialities about this
particular culture because of which this
culture has survived
good question good question um
so firstly i would not agree i mean you
do not say that but many people said
that indian civilization has survived i
would say that indian civilization
stopped existing in 1947. in 1947 india
officially became a secular socialist
country and abandoned the principles and
the values of
dharma so indian civilization stopped
existing at that point so we still have
culture that people keep on practicing
but the state is hindu phobic it is
culture and civilization that's what it
is now why did indian culture
survive this far thus far it's because
of india's enormous plurality
if you have a monochromatic one
dimensional
population the same ethnicity same
language and the same practices it is
very easy to destroy it
but in india there are so many different
languages there are so many
manifestations of indian culture so many
different gods and goddesses that
everybody worships which are all
manifestations of the ultimate reality
and that's how it is perceived and we
have so many different traditions if you
go from district to district you will
find the food changing the practices
changing the language changing the
dialect changing the traditions changing
and yet it is all representative of the
overarching
umbrella of indian civilization that's
why because of this incredible diversity
in plurality the foreigners were not
able to eradicate indian culture if you
look at persia the persians the parshwa
people they were our they were
descendants of ancient indians who were
migrated to the west to to what is now
called persia they were a uniform
population they were all the same
ethnicities small population same
ethnicity same language same practice it
was so easy in 20 30 years the entire
zoroastrian culture was gone
because of this uniformity
in india
the
subcontinent is enormous it is a
subcontinent it's not a country it's a
subcontinent and there is so much
diversity so because of this this what
we call the diversity it it ended up
becoming india's strength and that's why
the foreigners were despite their best
efforts they were not able to eradicate
everything about indian culture and
civilization so today it still persists
but today what's happened is that we
have a monochromatic education system a
one-dimensional education system that is
permeating the minds of every child so
today
after our so-called independence we are
seeing the rapid eradication and erosion
of indian culture and values so that is
a big threat today but until now we
survived because that thing was not in
place so that's what i can say
thank you sir it was an honor
thank you so much nice meeting you sir
thank you
bye thank you bye
okay
mr sahas
hello
hello sir uh
nice to meet you
sir the question i want to ask is and
i'm pretty sure many people at my age
college going students will relate to it
sir our teachers are a bunch of
anglophiles they are just in love with
the white skin
and they are so disconnected from the
reality of this country it's hilarious
so sir my question is that teaching is
one such profession that you will get a
new wave of teachers at least after
10-15 years
so sir will we just let
hi oh sorry i think there was some
disconnection please please repeat that
please
yes sir so i was saying that uh our
teachers are anglophiles so sir my
question is that teaching is one such
profession where you'll get a new wave
of teachers at least after 10 15 years
so yes will we just let our students get
brainwashed by these people till then
or is there any way out
so very good question very good question
so i will yes so what you observed is
correct most of our teachers i would say
are are i don't blame them for it it's
because their teachers taught them the
same thing and it's continuing
yeah this tradition is continuing
generation after generation so every
generation of teachers brainwashes a new
generation of kids and many of them
become teachers and that
tradition continues now
the thing is this uh in the indian
education system see in any
education system in a good education
system the stakeholders
should be the students
we are doing this for the students the
students have the rights and the
privileges that are above everybody else
but in the indian education system the
teachers and the staff are the
stakeholders and the students are just
the victims of the hostages
so the the ones who get the most rights
and privileges is the teachers and the
staff they take priority and precedence
about about everything else
imagine that a student misbehaves in
school what's going to happen the school
student will be expelled
now imagine a teacher or staff
misbehaves nothing will happen that
tells you who's the who's the real
stakeholder right
so they are so what's happened is that
this is a self-serving system and they
want to keep it going just the way it
has been going for the past 150 years
they don't want any changes changes are
uh uncomfortable changes are painful
just keep it going keep the routine
going
and
because the other thing is that it also
serves the the
the system which wants indians to be
mentally colonized indians should remain
mentally colonized indians should not
become thinkers and leaders indians
should be sheep
so this colonial system has been going
on and that's what they want to continue
so the new teachers that come out every
15 20 years they are themselves victims
of this as children and as when they
grow up they they grow up with the same
belief that the teachers put them in
their heads so it continues so what
needs to happen
uh see the who controls and and sustains
the education system we don't do it the
government does it the government passes
the rules they they regulate the
education system they pass they decide
the policies and they issue the funding
and of course there is this private
education now which has become a huge
business so in that case it is all about
money
so what needs to happen is that the
government at some point in time needs
to decide
that the time is now right that we
revise and reform the education system
we make the citizens and the children
the stakeholders not the teachers today
the education system is essentially an
employment generation scheme the only
purpose is to generate more employment
for teachers for staff and to generate
money for the owners of the of the
private schools their students are
merely hostages and victims so that
attitude needs to change and it will not
change unless the government forces it
forces it to change so unfortunately
it's not in our hands the government has
to do it
hopefully one of these days
it will happen i guess hope i hope so
yes sir right sir i read this very cute
comment in one of your streams sir that
abhijit ji is that one cool uncle we all
wished we had so thank you for being
that cool uncle
most welcome to the most welcome thank
you thank you
thank you yeah thank you bye
all right all right let's uh bring in
somebody else
okay let's bring in shreyas hi shreyas
hi hi sir uh
yes yes don't be so serious relax
so i'm from
maharashtra mumbai okay
so my question is very simple
uh what is the invisible hand that you
talk about
in encoding okay good question
so the invisible hand so the this term
i did not coin it this term was coined
sometime in the middle of the 19th
century and guess who coined this term
invisible hand
it was the great shri shri karl marx who
coined this term
the great marx the great father of all
the marxists you know he is the one who
coined this term invisible hand he said
that there is an invisible hand that
guides and controls world events so all
the governments and all these kingdoms
and all these things they are just
the superficial aspect of what we see
but there is something a deeper hidden
reality
a bunch of people who hold their true
reigns of power who hold all the money
and who are controlling events from
behind the scenes that's what he said
now as we know karl marx whether we like
him or not he was not a conspiracy
theorist he was not a conspiracy
theorist he's in the west is one of the
most respected thinkers
he's even considered to be one of one of
the great philosophers of the west sir
in
yes yes yes good good point so the thing
is he was not a conspiracy theorist so
if he observed this there must be some
reality to it and if there was an
invisible hand in the 19th century i'm
sure it continued until the 20th century
and maybe it still exists in the 21st
century so what you see is that there is
what you see
i mean uh let me just make a
joke
so
some people allege this this is an
allegation made by conspiracy theories
so you don't take it completely
seriously you can take it with a handful
of salt they say that
conspiracy theorists say
that when you are elected the president
of the u.s
they take you to a room they take you to
a room where you get to finally meet the
people who really run the country
you know that's what they say conspiracy
theorists so that could be possibly what
they mean by the invisible hand and
there could be a controlling force
elsewhere also that is controlling
global affairs perhaps possibly that is
the concept of the end of the invisible
hand which has been around since at
least the 19th century now i had
jokingly said that it is believed that
the the invisible hand speaks english
i had said that jokingly but i would say
it's also possible that maybe the
invisible
invisible hand speaks german or some
european language i'm not sure because i
don't know man i'm just i'm just
guessing if it even exists does it speak
um
not yet because the chinese have thus
far not been anywhere it's just the last
30 years that they've risen so maybe 100
years in the future
i would say it is a bunch of puppets
they are merely mercenaries they are not
thought leaders or they are not powerful
enough they they simply act as spoilers
within india
at the behest of
of what you could call invisible hand or
something from the invisible hand
all right sir okay nice to meet you
nice to meet you good question
invisible hand bye
good night goodness bye
okay let's just bring in whom shall we
bring in mr
hello hello hello sir
hi
my name is kushagra uh i'm from germany
but from but
but i live in punjab in india
all right all right nice to meet you sir
what's your question hello yeah my
question is related to the last question
that you answered
it's like
do you think that google and the current
internet that we are using
was a pilot project of
us government or the intelligence agency
and
and what these uh companies like youtube
uh google and apple what what do these
companies do with the data that we that
they
take it from us
good question so what i can tell you is
that uh the internet itself was a darpa
project darpa is the
the us
equivalent of drdo but it is far
superior to drdo drdo and darpa they
were founded in the same year
both in the same year but darpa has gone
way way way ahead of drdo because of
various reasons now so this the the
darpa scientists the researchers there
they came up with this idea of
interlinking
computers
across geographies and have these
computers uh talk to each other they
called it arpa net a r p a n e t r p net
and this arpa net became the basis of
what we now call the internet so
eventually uh
this system was expanded firstly it was
mainly defense computer then i think
there was a network of academic
computers in various universities and
eventually it expanded to
become a network of all computers
connected globally so that is the
internet so that is how the internet was
born it was i think in the 1960s or 70s
or something that the first pilot
testing was done uh i don't remember the
dates you can look it up now what i can
say is this uh today as you know data is
a precious commodity data is the new oil
i do not believe that google or whatever
was a us government pilot project but
what i do what we do know is that
it it is located in the u.s it is
it's part of the us system and therefore
i am sure the u.s government must be in
a position to to
use the data to to access the data and
use it in various per in in various ways
uh this gentleman edward snowden had
revealed something called prism
yeah so in prism what you had you had a
synthesis of various data sources into
one big picture and you could see what's
happening what is the sentiment in any
particular geography in the world at any
given time and you could even play on
the sentiments and
shape the sentiments and beliefs and
feelings of people by trending certain
hashtags or whatever you know something
like that so that's what prism was
that's like more than 10 years ago today
there will be something else much more
advanced in place i do not doubt that
the americans are good at this
and so
that would essentially involve a
synthesis of data from various sources
not only google but
amazon youtube bing
and various other things which i i'm
just i'm just speculating i don't have
any actual information it's just an
educated guess so uh
so that's what i can say i can only make
an educated guess that something like
that may be there in place must be there
in place i mean if you have all access
to all this information why would you
not use it
anybody would do that i mean i saw that
the snowden movie in that it was shown
exactly like that and that's why i think
china doesn't have the uh have the
firewall in the country to protect
themselves from the usa yes and the
other yes
yes yes you're right good question sir
thank you have a nice night
you're really good i saw your first
video in like 2020
and that was really good the books that
you mentioned i have not read all of
them but they were really good thank you
for
just do just keep doing this work thank
you bye thank you so much thank you so
much appreciate it
thank you bye
okay um
shivam mr shivam
hello
can you hear me can you see me
hello sir
hello hello how are you doing
yes yes
okay i guess you're not able to hear me
so we'll bring you in later
uh
whom shall we bring in let's bring in mr
bhutas brutus
mr brutus
hi sir
how are you hey
i am how are you doing where are you
from
i'm from mumbai
do you remember
samira is the assyrian queen right yes
yes yes yes
okay you would like to know about her
so what i can tell you is not much
[Laughter]
was
an assyrian queen i don't remember when
she lived maybe in the first or second
millennium bc maybe
she is as far as i remember the first
woman
to hold a significant position of power
in this region west of persia
there may be parts of persia in her
kingdom
and she was the
wife of one of the kings who died or
something and she was very powerful she
was the first woman like i said to hold
the power and become an actual queen in
her own right
and as far as the records
are there they seem to indicate that she
attempted to go eastwards and
try an invasion of india which ended in
a defeat the indian king whose identity
i don't remember right now he was able
to defeat her forces and she was forced
to retreat and go back to her country so
that's what i can tell you in very brief
about her uh i think the information you
can read online yeah yeah yeah
i have read like um she has everything
around four thousand hearts and she just
left around 20
to back to go back
i have read this but i don't know it is
factual or not
so yeah the record seemed to indicate
that she tried
invading
thank you so much thank you so much
thank you bye
okay let's bring in mr chinmay
cinemaji good evening sir good day sir
hello where are you from
so i'm from district maharashtra
very nice to meet you sir very nice to
meet you
sir my question is sir uh what according
to you is the best strategy to do to
deal with the
left-wing extremism in india
and uh why don't india conduct a
surgical strike type of operation
against the national lights like i mean
bombing by helicopters or
aircrafts thank you okay okay good
question uh so what i would say is this
uh
they may be naxalites they may be
criminals but they are indian citizens
and we should not bomb them we should
try to apprehend see this is not a
military operation this is a civilian
problem
they may be bearing arms and all that
they may be doing that
but they're not pakistanis they're not
foreigners they are our own citizens so
we should
at least give them a certain
extra privilege as indian citizens that
we will not bomb them from the air we
should not bomb
uh
indian citizens from the air what i
would say what should be done what
should be done about these
insurgents terrorists etc the first
thing that needs to happen is cut off
their sources of foreign funding
see these people they are getting
funding from somewhere they are being
coordinated from somewhere and they are
getting arms and ammunition from
somewhere
identify these sources and cut off the
funding and and ensure that that funding
the source of the funding is targeted
and dealt with and neutralized
so most of these sources of funding etc
they're from uh
india
historically it's been like that i mean
there have been books written about this
article written about this most of these
people are funded from abroad whether it
is from china whether it is from
pakistan or various other places
invisible hands wherever it is
so find out where this is coming from
and cut off the sources of funding that
itself will take care of 95 of the
problem now if something still persists
do a police action with crpf or whatever
go and apprehend the criminals or
terrorists and then deal with them
according to the indian law that's what
i would suggest so the
problem
it has its roots in foreign funding it
is foreign actors who are funding
and supporting insurgencies and
terrorist activities within india that
is the entire naxalite problem the
so-called red belt problem which can be
dealt with
in this manner i am sure i mean as we
can see before 2014 this was a huge
problem in india very large portions of
central india were not under the control
of the indian state of the indian
government
today that has that problem has shrunk
down the cancer has shrunk because of
chemotherapy to a very large extent now
it is not that much prevalent in central
india or other parts of india you still
have some of it so i am sure the
government if it
who am i to tell them what to do they
know better than me but that is the uh
way to go about it i would say right
so i think the response should be more
humane
as far as indian citizens and
non-military actors are concerned we can
have a
more calibrated approach towards them
thank you
bye
okay um let's bring in whom shall we
bring
in uh somebody who's been waiting for a
while let's bring in mr uh
somya brata
hello
i cannot hear you sir
can't hear you
hi
hi hello sir uh my question was about
the
bangladesh liberation war in 1971 as you
have heard in our school so that
bangladesh immigration was the ethnocyte
and genocide conducted against the
bengal community but if we see the
statistics and many books written on it
by an american journalist named
and mean
the book name is the blood telegram in
which he informs that most of the people
were killed were from the hindu
community and also
when the operations are started
by the pakistan army in the dhaka and
the village areas most of the
victims were hindus and only those
muslims were killed who supported the
hindus and the abomination at that time
and also we know that sheikh mujibur
rahman
before the uh formation of abba mili
he uh he was the
remember of the muslim league and was a
close associate of the surah
gang
so why this uh
this fact has been
brushed under the carpet that it was a
side uh not a religious genocide if you
see 20 million people out of 30 were
hindus only that was the question
yes
the problem
is that uh any atrocities
against hindus uh it's always been the
policy of the west
uh to brush it under the carpet
the west
this is the thing is this is a clash of
civilizations actually our civilization
has survived despite a thousand years of
brutalization and oppression and they
don't like it
according to them what should have
happened is that india should have been
totally westernized indian culture
civilization should have been wiped out
and we should have been become part of
their market that they can sell things
too and
so the thing is that if you look at the
western academics they have a policy
of
deriding and expressing contempt towards
indian culture it's a policy all the
anglophile english speaking western
academics have this policy that even if
you're teaching indian history you have
to distort it show it from a certain
perspective and you must make fun
of hinduism you have to be contemptuous
towards hinduism and indian culture
that's been their policy
and this is simply in line with the
policy to uh
to kind of water down whatever
atrocities happened against hindus
whether it is bangladesh or whether
whether it is in the past 1000 years of
indian history also i mean you know if
you look at the past thousand years of
indian history i can assure you that at
least 100 million indians must have died
or maybe 500 million years over a
thousand years but that is not
recognized in any textbook in any
history book anywhere in the world right
right the british themselves killed at
least 100 million indians mostly were
hindus right because of their
artificially engineered famines now in
the bangladesh genocide
i would the official figures are 1.5
million is it
my far distant relative who used to live
in bangladesh
district
he was
attacked by the pakistani army his
family and the local collaborators of
the pakistani alberta islamist group was
the bengal on islamic fundamental group
who supported that group
so basically there were many bengali
muslims supporting pakistan army
and targeting yes specifically
yeah so that's the other reason lots of
bangladeshis were collaborators in this
and uh many of them became prominent
politicians and local leaders etc after
1971.
and
because of that it was also good for
them to kind of suppress all the truths
about what happened in 1971 that all of
them were collaborating with the
pakistani army and in in conducting the
genocide
i think the figure of 1.5 million hindus
is actually
an under representation of what must
have really happened
right
here
also in dhaka recently few skeletons
have been found and those skeletons
identified as bengali hindus were killed
by the pakistani army
there must be many more than under the
carpet
yeah yes then yeah
that's the policy yeah so good question
and uh nice meeting you
thank you thank you
hello
tanish hi
i can hear you sir where are you from
so i am from maharashtra and i'm living
in bangalore
yeah so my question is like uh
like the india is on the wrong path like
we need to get it on the right path
like we need to do many reforms like get
it to the civilizational group so for
all that we need a
dictatorship
so we need a divider
so fort so in the future if we get
like a like a good leader he has to
become a dictator
but then when he tries to do that india
will become destabilized
so whenever a country becomes
destabilized like the other countries
can take collect advantage of that like
china can do some war or something
so how can someone like uh
become a dictator without destabilizing
the country or like should he be like
the invisible hand of india
uh
very interesting question so first of
all i would not say that i am in favor
of a dictator or something x or y or z i
what i would say is that whatever works
best
try that
whether it is a monarchy whether it's a
dictatorship whether it's democracy a
form of democracy or b form of democracy
doesn't matter
it doesn't matter what color the cat is
as long as it catches mice so what we
need is india needs to rise again india
needs to rise to its historical position
of at least one third of the world's gdp
right that's the first thing and india
should be of
it it should be it should have long term
uh security and prosperity
that is what we seek now
let's say hypothetically that you want
to install a dictator in india in india
so that it becomes easier to reach this
position hypothetically
so
if somebody tries to be a dictator
they're going to face a position that's
the just the way of the world
now how does one become a dictate
dictator despite all of this opposition
how do you do it look at history look at
examples in history in the past 1000
years
how did in the past thousand years or in
any country in the world how did uh
let's say you have people people like
napoleon you have people like uh
like mustafa kemal ataturk do you have
people like changes khan how did these
people rise from nothing
assume the reigns of power and succeed
to whatever extent they succeeded if you
study their life history and whatever
tactics and strategies are used you will
understand how a dictator can rise
a consolidated power and take the
country forward so if you study history
you will get all the answers i don't i
cannot give you all the details because
it will take a lot a lot of time there
are lots of things that a person
needs to overcome in order to rise to
the stage to that status so the last
such example successful example
would be mustafa himala in turkey is
there any other more recent successful
example i'm not quite sure maybe there
is
and maybe there's not let's see but
that's what i can say that the history
world history offers you all the lessons
you need so
so these principles of power there are
timeless principles
you can adapt them for any time period
whether it is 5000 bc or the 21st
century the principles remain the same
but you have to adapt them according to
the
local time frame in the situation
all right sir yes so that's it
all right thank you good question
bye
okay um
mr devi prasanna
hello
yes sir hello uh i hope you can hear me
i can hear you sir nice to see you where
are you from
sir i am from odisha and i live in
bhuvanese actually and uh beautiful and
so glad to finally
have a chance to talk to you it was
really a race clicking in that to join
this room and to get a chance to talk
with you because i'm a i mean i've been
watching you for almost two years now
and
it's really educational because all that
fairy tales that we have read from our
history and crt books
all those things and the real uh history
when we read from other books like the
saffron swords and the
books that you recommend and those are
really educational and i actually had a
question when this uh
start when this podcast started but
i um my mind stuck in the question which
someone asked before that was about uh
the
sati pratha
that india faced during that british era
but actually no one talks about the
truth that salem which trials the things
that happened in europe and they burned
the women's and called them witches
um something also happened in like that
in russia too
so i want to know why those things are
suppressed and this sati prasa is
like
spoke around because
there it was a huge problem now we see
it in some
like in some tv series and some episodes
i want to know your views in this
very good question it's a very good
question so it's like this uh if you
look at the number of women that were
burned forcibly alive as witches in in
europe it would far exceed the real
cases of sati in india which were all
voluntary you may have a handful of
cases in india real hard recorded
evidence just a handful of cases in the
case of europe you had i don't know tens
or hundreds of thousands of maybe tens
of thousands of women who were burned
alive forcibly as now why is
that not emphasized and why are they
keep keeping on lying about india it's
very simple the world doesn't work on
the basis of principles and truth we
keep on uh shouting the slogan satyam
the world doesn't work like that the
world works on the basis of us
that's what happens people will
speak untruths and lies
to to further their self-interest
now in the west what they wanted and
this what they still want is they want
to eradicate hinduism and indian culture
from india and they want to
spread their culture here and they want
indians to first feel that their that
indian culture is primitive it is
backward it is barbaric misogynistic so
that's why they keep on spreading these
lies about the so-called sati pratha it
was not a pratha it was a very rare
thing
but
what they did to their women they will
just try to brush it under the carpet
because it is very inconvenient right
because that is a hard fact that they
cannot deny so instead of denying it
they will just not talk about it and if
they don't talk about it then nobody
will come to know see for us indians it
is most of us don't even know that they
had this practice of burning women as
and they had this horrific
misogynistic culture in some parts of
europe until the 1990s women did not
have the right to vote
in some parts of europe until the 1990s
women did not have the right to vote can
you believe it and that's where the
feminism concept started
exactly so it is all hypocrisy so what
we need to do
is instead of getting emotional i'm not
saying you are being emotional i'm
saying all of us
we indians are very emotional people so
i'm just saying in general let's not be
emotional let's seek out all the facts
the facts are in our favor they are the
ones who are lying they are the ones who
are trying to suppress the truth about
their horrific past
let's just all speak about it go to
twitter go to facebook go wherever you
are active on social media and tweet
about it twice a day let's see now how
they will hide this so that's what needs
to happen the world unfortunately is not
a place where
truth wins
propaganda always wins but if all of us
get together and we all speak the truth
in unison then their propaganda will
fail so that's what we need to do
yes also that all the sexual harassment
or more in europe than in india but
still we feel ourselves that uh more
number of sectors that our country is
more backward but in the
other case around it is the truth yes
yes yes okay thank you so much
actually my original question was to ask
you about the nep the national education
policy but um i'm sorry you you can only
take one
question so
if you can just share something
it's a very big policy i think i think
it's not really effective that's what i
can tell you we need better reforms
okay so yes sir
i think our nice brilliance
thank you thank you thank you so much
thank you thank you take care bye
okay
uh whom shall i bring in
i shall bring in mr
shashank
hello
you know
four to five years at least and you know
i told my parents and families also to
watch you because
what they taught us you know what they
are taught in this course
so and we are very satisfied with your
conclusion and answer sir i have a doubt
from the mahabharata
i uh when one of your videos i have i
watched and you said that
uh regarding the dronacharya on eclipse
and i agree on that what have you said
that you know dronacharya did to the
eclipse
but on the karma part you said that
karna wasn't great
and this strike my mind sir but his
deeds are you know all famous after
becoming king his loyalty to his
his to his friend duryodhan
in spite of being you know he know he
knows that you know i am the son of
kunti
and
then then also he you know didn't
revolted against the empire that is
thrown his minds many none of the
draupadis incidents i i'm not with that
karna part but
apart from this that you know
sacrificed a lot and even he he he
spared the life of the pandyas and even
the krishna also told to arjuna that
it's i who saved you from the karna
otherwise and the hanuman's uh you know
flashlights
so my question was you you said that the
karna wasn't great sir so on what aspect
you're saying that karna wasn't great
again
okay okay so i'll tell you this see
there is no doubt that he was a very
good warrior better than most warriors
better than 99.9 of warriors right he
was an elite class warrior really really
strong person very good archer very good
warrior no doubt about it
right but that is not all there is to a
human being
a good human being has to be
well-rounded it is very clearly
mentioned in the mahabharat that he was
a rude person he was short-tempered he
was abusive to people so that is a
drawback which let's say arjun did not
have the second thing is like you said
he was a loyal person right he was loyal
to
to duryodhana
now tell me something sir
are you supposed to be loyal to your
friend even though he is evil or are you
supposed to be loyal to dharma
no i will are you supposed to take the
side of the dharma or are you supposed
to take the night of your friend who is
evil
who supported him all in all the
instances but it here when the pandya's
pandavas discriminated him
after no no no no no no discrimination
what discriminate please okay let's see
what is the uh what example do you have
of discrimination
and all of these that but
it's like this it's like this there is
this tournament okay
there is this archery tournament that's
going on
it is a tournament for the royal princes
correct
let's go let's examine let's let's
imagine the situation okay you are in
england
and the
sons of the king
are practicing
archery now let's say a carpenter's son
comes there and says bye mojave
let me also participate what's going to
happen
i agree i agree on you on your point but
after after some time when you knew that
he is the son of the kunti
and even after that he didn't tell
anyone and you know told anyone about
his you know
truth and despite of that he fought you
know
under the rule of uh duryodhana so
wasn't he sacrificing and the second
more
say it's like this sir life is not
always fair
life is not fair
if you believe that everybody is going
to go by the rules and be principled and
all that you're not going to have a good
life
i'm not talking about you specifically
i'm saying to everybody that life is not
fair you will face injustice in life
people will not act according to certain
principles that you believe in people
are going to be unjust to you people
will be unfair to you but does it mean
that you should take the side of our
dharma
or does it mean that you should still be
steadfast and follow dharma this is the
only simple choice that karna had and
unfortunately he took the side of the
kawarawas and and injustice
and that's what happened to him that's
what i can say from a big picture
perspective if you want to go into every
detail we can speak for hours but that's
not bad
thank you so much sir but i was just one
point sir even the pandavas also when
they you know
in the
game of dice when did what they did to
these
that was also not acceptable and it was
i agree with you i agree with you you
are one hundred percent right what
yudhish said did
do you know
let me explain something
when the war ended what did shri krishna
say to the pandavas
go to the himalayas and spend whatever
life is left over there
none of you deserves to be the king
yudhisthira was a compulsive gambler a
man who gambled away his brothers and
his family and his wife did he did a
person like him deserve to be king he
was not worthy of being the king
you are right your point is 100 valid
arjun was a great warrior but when the
time came for him to fight he was like i
can't fight
was it deserving of being a king no
these these are the lessons of the
mahabharat these are the two lessons of
the mahabharata so we have to learn that
and we have to understand that so even
the pandavas were wrong in many places
right yes
nice question nice talking to you sir
namaste
nice to meet you nice to meet you sir
nice to meet you too bye
okay
shivam is very enthusiastic let's bring
in mr shivam
what's
nice to talk to you sir uh
so i have a question i have written it
so
in your uh opinion like if you become a
capitalist country
uh
populist society instead of being a
mixed economy
so would india is the status of
and uh
how many years it will take and will the
new entrepreneurial will help it like
uh capitalism is a very quick way of
getting very prosperous as we can see
with the with the americans and all
especially if you have uh
predatory capitalism and capitalistic
imperialism if you practice all these
various policies in conjunction together
then you will get very prosperous very
quickly at the expense of other
countries and at the expense of the
planet
because capitalism
is about quarter upon cro quarter profit
every quarter your company must show
profit and this is a never ending cycle
of profit you have to continuously be
profitable on
so it is about infinite profits on a
finite planet what's going to happen
it's going to destroy the planet because
we are plundering the planet for
resources
right so capitalism in the short term is
going to make any country that does it
properly
very rich
like america
like america but see what they have done
to the planet the entire state of the
planet is because of what the west has
done and the americans essentially what
is america it is
the continuation
of the
british empire
the british had this downfall but the
americans are the descendants of the
british and they took it forward so that
is the continuation of the british
empire they have this global empire
today whether you like it or not that's
what it is it's called a superpower but
there is a euphemism for an imperial
power because they sell their weapons
like
to any other country
to reach
their goal
so
how can we uh reach
that sonic is status so at this state at
this where we are right now we have to
pursue unfortunately the same policies
we have to develop entrepreneurship
industrialization manufacturing all
those things
okay and hopefully once we reach a
certain status we're able to we
we can maybe change the way of doing
things
it to be to to be more sustainable and
let the planet live longer i would say
but at this stage the way the world
works we have to work within those
parameters
the entire global system is such that
you can succeed currently only with
capitalism
there is no other way out
so if india wants to rise it has to play
the play by the same rules
that's why just like america yes
hopefully
okay
okay thank you
thank you can you just uh say my family
are high they are watching your program
on the tv in the dining room hi to
everybody from shivamji's family namaste
nice to see you all
take care bye
okay let's bring in mr rahul who has
been waiting patiently hello ji
good evening good day
what's your question
the sound is not clear unfortunately
my understanding is
i'm really i'm really sorry
your voice is not clear at all i'm not
able to understand so i i really
apologize but it's it's not audible
properly so what i'm going to do
hello so now is it uh
whatever
yes now it is audible you have done
something right yes sir please go ahead
so
my question is my question uh i can't
say what you think but uh
because you know what i'm still in
nervous
don't be nervous relax it's just me
my question is that
i want to know about
the caucasian arrest where did they come
from because my understanding is that
the caucasian people are the people of
indian descent who settled in caucasus
and they invaded most of the europe and
europe is completely basic and they may
say that because due to christianity we
are civilized no no never because this
is the basic thing uh still you can find
the words of vedas in europe so
according to me
quotation are the people of
india
okay okay okay so what is the origin of
the caucasian race is the question
uh see first of all that the concept of
race is pseudo scientific there is no
such thing as a race there is no such
thing as a pure race there is no such
thing as the boundary between one race
and another race even the concept of
species is kind of blurry
right so what i can say is this the
origin of the people of europe uh if you
look at the the genetic history of
europe you will find that most europeans
especially in western europe are the
descendants of the so-called yamnaya
invaders who invaded europe from the
east about 5000 years before today
and if we look at the genetics of these
so-called yamnaya people you will find a
certain lineage a certain patrilineal
lineage which is passed on from father
to sun over thousands of years and this
patrilineal lineage or haplogroup is
called r1b
now if you look at the history of r1b
you will find that it originates in
india which kind of tells you that these
yamnaya people were originally people
who went out of india at some point in
time a few thousand years before today
and then they eventually ended up
invading and conquering europe and
changing the genetic history of europe
so that's the origin of the europeans of
course there is other genetics also
involved in that the skin color keeps
changing now again skin color if you
look at the origin of the fair skin
color the white white skin color that
genetic mutation also originates in
india strangely enough so in india you
find all kinds of different variations
in europe you find uniformity of skin
color more or less yes sir
because the explanation i will give or
why it is the indian
origin is that we know because
india was not originally
it was an asian continent right at the
time
india india had some tectonic movement
yes
let's
let's understand tectonics
tectonics takes hundreds of millions of
years to happen
the movement from africa to asia of the
indian subcontinent took at least 100
million years
the human species homo sapiens is not
even a million years old so there is no
connection with africa right
the history of the human species of homo
sapiens is less than 250 million 250 000
years old or maybe 300 000 years old
that's it so it has nothing to do with
tectonics there is no relation
all right
okay thank you
because most of them have this confusion
about the concept known as derma because
they will be confused for
intellect and the body full of spirit
and the soul full of devotion creates
dharma because you know
his mind was
completely
uh what is that
he was not unsure about
doing the
supporting
his mind was completely far away from
what he was doing so he was disturbed in
his mind so he became mother me
that's what my understanding about
all right all right thank you thank you
for that thank you for uh sharing your
views thank you thank you
i get it i get it all right thank you
nice meeting you sir take care bye
okay let's bring in somebody else um
okay let's bring in mr rishabh
currently i'm in us
nice very good
and so my question is uh like
about a vikrama aditya uh sir it is said
that uh his uh empire uh was
india spread through india saudi arabia
and even some parts of russia also and
it it was covered in ira some parts of
iran was also there
and
and so why our history book does not
tell about that and like uh
currently like uh the current government
it is that that it's a right-wing
government so why they are not uh
changing their syllabus of history it's
been almost 10 years they are in the
power
okay okay yeah good question see first
of all uh i have no idea what the
government is planning to do and why did
they do certain things they don't do
certain things i am not privy to
what goes on in in the
what the plans are and all that so i
cannot answer on their behalf maybe we
should ask the minister of whoever is in
charge of that
so i cannot answer on the behalf on
their behalf now when it comes to
emperor vikramaditya there is a lot of
ambiguity there is a lot of confusion
about the identity of this great emperor
clearly we have this uh
this uh
this story that
that does not give go away that we had a
great emperor called vikramaditya who
had a great empire and there is a vikram
somewhat ira also named after him so uh
and our historians they claim that this
is a mythical emperor
he did not exist in reality that's what
they claim i think that's nonsense
i think this great emperor must have
existed but the problem is we don't know
exactly when he existed we don't uh
because the historians and
archaeologists have not done their job
that's why we don't have a way of
pinpointing
when
he would have been in power in india at
what it in what historical period he
would have been in power
it is said he was before jesus christ
uh yeah i don't want to mix him up with
jesus and all that i will relate him to
various other indian eras of history
like you said he most likely was before
the a.d period
but we don't have sufficient information
about him to make a proper assessment
of when he lived
where his capital is supposed to be
ojain i believe yeah
yeah but we also don't know how big the
empire was people make various claims
but we don't have
hard unambiguous evidence and that's why
it's almost impossible for me to say
whether it's true or not that he had
this big empire which went all these
places or not i don't know
i don't know all i can say is on the
basis of evidence i will give you
answers but we don't have evidence yes
uh it is said that his empire was still
turkey also and there is a one library
name
uh like uh there was some famous scholar
in turkey and he said that whoever lived
at that period was a golden era so
from that we can conclude that
his empire was taken to anything
we cannot make conclusions without
evidence now they say there is a library
in which there is a book which says that
where is the book show me the book show
me a photograph why doesn't everybody
anyone show me i have not seen a single
photograph or picture of this book where
it says so and so and so
without that sort of evidence how can we
make conclusions
maybe we are trying to hide it sure yeah
but we have not seen the evidence yeah
uh he is i'm forgetting his name but uh
he has that that's why so so like
yeah okay so
it's like this i can also make a claim
that so-and-so was great and all but it
is just words of mouth
it's just hearsay it is not hard
evidence there is a difference between
somebody making a claim and somebody
substantiating a claim with evidence
that is is tenable in a court of law for
instance that is hard evidence right so
we don't have that unfortunately
unfortunately i don't believe that he's
a mythical emperor but i don't have
sufficient evidence but uh but uh he he
has the big empire we can say that
and uh no
no no on what basis do we say that
on what basis do we
yeah
right
yes
that's what i can say
all right nice meeting you sir
take care
uh
i may have time for one last question
let's bring in mr chandra kant
hello so i'm from bangalore and i have
this question regarding the academy
regarding the academy throughout the
world as in it is already left leaning
and uh
i had gone through a recent
documents and a few uh talks as well
that say that there is already a
pre-ordained kind of uh
way that the humanitarian research goes
on like they want to push their agenda
by asking certain questions while doing
research they want to tease out a
certain answer that already supports
their
you know pre-existing uh beliefs or
whatever they want to say and that their
uh research is actually passive like how
do we as a developing country which
already has such things such views i
mean
you know pushed on us and how do we uh
come out of it like
uh how do we make research such that
we come out of such a point of views and
uh yeah look at issues as it is rather
than having a preset uh you know thought
behind it
yeah i get it yes right that's a very
good question so what needs to happen is
we need to reform our our academic
system which is part of the larger
education system the academia is
essentially the highest level of the
education system which is their college
and university level uh research work
that's what it is so we need to
decolonize this and reform it so right
now what happens is that there is this
entrenched mafia in the academic system
it is there is this stranglehold of
leftist academics in all the humanities
departments and it's even
going into the iits and everything right
now so that's what's existing right now
what needs to happen is we need to
decontaminate academia remove all the
marxist academics whether they like it
or not i'm saying remove them from their
positions i'm not saying remove them
from anything else
and we need to
have better standards we need to ensure
that the university system it is
research oriented not teaching oriented
teaching should happen of course but
there should be research and genuine
original research there should be high
standards promotions and all that needs
to be done on the basis of performance
and research not your seniority or
whatever it is today and nobody should
have a guaranteed job for life because
that makes them
entrenched forever so we need a
systematic set of reforms in place in
the academic system especially in the
universities where the research comes
from where all the books are written and
all that so all that needs to be done
properly in with good planning in a
systematic manner we need to
decontaminate decontaminate
the academic system we need to ensure
that all the sources of foreign funding
are removed because all of these
academics
are funded by
foreign sources so these things need to
happen if we do that then we will have a
new crop of academics and researchers
who look at the world from without
without these blinkers with with a clear
view
and then you it will the research will
be done on the basis of facts and logic
and not on the basis of ideology which
is what's happening right now what
indicates this also is that of the fact
that uh the western research is more
passive uh compared to what our
civilizational research was because if
you even if you look at i i have read a
partial transcript of regulator
and the way the research goes in that is
rather constructive compared to what
left i mean what west does now because
west takes up a research already done
they have that view and then upon that
the research only to confirm the already
existing research but it is it was not
so in our uh civilization like
everything was constructive even if you
look at adi shankaracharya you compare
his works to this to his predecessor's
work it was uh totally deviant like it
was completely new
i mean such
what's your opinion on that
i agree i agree i agree with you okay
yeah thanks thanks for the question
it's a great opportunity
thank you so much nice meeting you bye
all right uh let's bring in mr vedant
one person who's been waiting for a very
long time last person for today how are
you sir
i have too um questions but first i
would like to ask that is uh
uh talking about kailash for what uh
uh if we see if i if you see kailash
prabhupada on google maps so it comes
under china so
it is uh it is popular because of
hinduism culture but then also why it
comes under china and
by any time we can reconquer it
okay good question so the question is
why does the great sacred mountain mount
kailash
why is it currently controlled by the
chinese by the chinese communist party
that's the question
you know why it's like that
it's because the world is not fair the
world doesn't work on the basis of
justice truth and principles the world
obeys only one law the law of the jungle
the big fish will eat the small fish
that's what happens so according to
truth righteousness and justice kailash
pervert should be part of india it
should be under indian control
but it is currently controlled by the
chinese so what should we do
we need to get stronger economically and
militarily and we need to then at the
right time
reincorporate that territory into india
or otherwise we can free tibet and keep
it under tibetan jurisdiction that's
what needs to happen so if you want to
get justice you have to first make sure
that you get strong enough and powerful
enough
to make your own justice for yourself
if you just keep on begging pleading
please please give me justice it's not
going to happen it's never going to
happen so that's what india needs to
learn that's what the people of india
need to learn there is no justice in the
world there is no fairness in the world
the world is a harsh place
if you want what you deserve
strengthen yourself empower yourself and
then you will get it otherwise you'll
never get it
that's how it works
all right sir
yes sir
good question thank you take care
thank you nice meeting you bye
okay ladies gentlemen i can see many
people trying to raise their hands
uh
okay
okay srikanji last person last last and
final
where is he
can you hear me
i can hear you yeah i'm from bangalore
uh but i'm doing my masters in
astrophysics here
and oh wow
yeah i i live in germany currently and i
really want your thoughts on this
initially when i came into germany and i
started studying in this system
uh i found it's really hard to
understand the math and physics behind
it because the scale of teaching is very
different than what we learn in india
but the profound difference i found
between us and
people like germans and japanese they
learn fundamental mathematics and
physics in their mother tongue
so their thought process is very very
clear and they can just have to
translate it to another language but in
our case we have to think in a language
that is not ours
so do you think
we should start teaching all these
things in
a in the native languages of
the various states such that we are firm
in our thinking and english should only
be a medium of translation what are your
thoughts on this i really would like to
know this is an excellent excellent
question my i have i am of the firm
let's look at history
if we look at the period before 1500 a.d
all of the scientific advancements all
of the scientific knowledge astronomical
knowledge it all came from india
via arabia into europe then they
translated into latin and that's how
they were able to build up what is known
today as modern science and
technology right so all of the
fundamental work whether it is algebra
trigonometry calculus astronomy whatever
was done in indian languages mostly
sanskrit yeah and
right yeah
so the argument that is made is that
english is the language of science and
technology without english will not be
able to do science what nonsense all of
the science was done in sanskrit and in
indian languages in the kerala school of
mathematics and where not what not so
what i firmly believe is that all of
these concepts should be taught in the
mother tongue of the child always that
is the fastest and most effective way to
learn anything especially mathematics
especially logic especially science yes
has to be taught in the mother tongue
then see how many geniuses come out of
india that's what needs to happen yeah
that's um i just wanted to comment
because when i was learning cosmology
here um right now they are teaching
about this big bang but there is not
much evidence leading further in that
direction so now there i've seen papers
coming out which says our universe is a
bouncing model but we already have in
our literature that our universe exists
as a brahma day and a brahmana night how
it comes into life and and people don't
are not willing to accept that this
stems from uh
indian
culture and indian
talk like literature
and now they are like this is a novel
idea this is the very such a proceed and
i find it funny so yeah that's what
thank you so much
indeed very good point that you've made
and i agree that all these concepts were
first conceived off in india
they're they're looking for looking to
our text for inspiration and then
they're saying we have discovered this
is a new idea what nonsense
yeah very good point very good
thank you
yeah nice meeting you thank you
thank you bye
alright uh ladies and gentlemen this is
the end of today's session very
interesting session i'm very glad to see
new faces very very interesting let's
keep doing this i apologize to those of
you who are waiting but this is truly
the end for today so let's keep doing
this i hope to meet all of you
and each i hope to give all of you a
chance to speak to me in the forthcoming
sessions
so take care and i will see you very
soon again take care bye